A Guide to the Warren Morton Washington Papers WW2008.001
National Center for Atmospheric Science Library Special Collections
A Guide to the Warren Morton Washington Papers, 1963-Present
Bulk, 1963-2007
WW2008.001
National Center for Atmospheric Science Library Special Collections
40.0 Linear feet Box 1, 9 folders Box 2, 6 folders Box 3, 22 folders Box 4, 9 folders Box 5, 12 folders Box 6, 16 folders Box 7, 29 folders Box 8, 20 folders Box 9, 17 folders Box 10, 7 folders Box 11, 25 folders Box 12, 17 folders Box 13, 14 folders Box 14, 8 folders Box 15, 32 folders Box 16, 14 folders Box 17, 14 folders Box 18, 26 folders Box 19, 4 folders Box 20, 32 folders Box 21, 21 folders Box 22, 10 folders Box 23, 11 folders Box 24, 13 folders Box 25, 6 folders Box 26, 10 folders Box 27, 17 folders Box 28, 9 folders Box 29, 9 folders Box 30, 13 folders Box 31, 8 folders Box 32, 14 folders Box 33, 20 folders Box 34, 7 folders Box 35, 9 folders, 1 binder Box 36, 4 folders Box 37, 36 folders Box 38, 9 folders, 1 bule folder Box 39, 7 folders
<subject>These papers document the career of Warren M. Washington, whose research has specialized in computer modeling of the earth's climate. Included are records documenting his work on issues of diversity in science, and his longtime role in numerous professional committees and organizations, as well as advisor to many governmental agencies and programs. His contributions to the field of atmospheric science are described in extensive files of correspondence, publications, reports, conferences and seminars, committee records, motion picture films, oral history interviews, and other materials.</subject>
<subject>40 cartons</subject>
Box 35
Box 37
Box 16
Box 17
Box 19
Box 28
Box 31
Box 33
Box 24
Box 25
Box 26
Box 4
Box 5
Box 7
Copyright status
<subject>The status of copyright in the unpublished writings of Warren M. Washington is governed by the Copyright Law of the United States (Title 17, U.S.C.).</subject>
Restrictions on Use and Access
Access to this collection is open, although there are some materials that are restricted. Researchers must request permission from the UCAR archivist to use those materials.
Biographical Note
Born in Portland, Oregon, in 1936, Warren Washington earned a bachelor's degree in physics and a master's degree in meteorology from Oregon State University. After completing his doctorate in meteorology at Pennsylvania State University, he joined NCAR in 1963 as a research scientist. He has published more than 100 papers in professional journals. His book, “An Introduction to Three-Dimensional Climate Modeling,” co-authored with Claire Parkinson, is a reference on climate modeling. The second edition was published in May, 2005. Washington is a consultant and advisor to a number of government officials and committees on climate system modeling. From 1978 to 1984, he served on the President's National Advisory Committee on Oceans and Atmosphere. He participated in several panels of the National Research Council and chaired its Advisory Panel for Climate Puzzle, a film produced for the 1986 PBS television series “Planet Earth.” Washington was a member of the Secretary of Energy's Advisory Board from 1990 to 1993 and has been on the Secretary of Energy's Biological and Environmental Research Advisory Committee (BERAC) since 1990. From 1996-2006, he served as the chair of the subcommittee on Global Change for BERAC. Washington held the office of President of the American Meteorological Society (AMS) in 1994, and was Past President in 1995. He served on the Modernization Transition Committee and the National Centers for Environment Prediction Advisory Committee of the U.S. National Weather Service. In 1998, he was appointed to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Agency Science Advisory Board. In May of 1995, he was appointed by President Clinton to a six-year term on the National Science Board (NSB). The NSB has dual responsibilities as national science policy adviser to the President and Congress, and as governing board for the National Science Foundation. In March 2000 he was nominated by President Clinton for a second six-year term and was confirmed by the Senate in September 2000. In May 2002, the NSB announced that it had elected Washington as its new Chair. He was re-elected to a second term in May of 2004. Washington's term ended on 10 May 2006. Washington is a Fellow of the AMS and a Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), and from 1991 to 1995 he was a member of the AAAS Board of Directors. He is a Distinguished Alumnus of Pennsylvania State University and Oregon State University, an Alumni Fellow of Pennsylvania State University and Oregon State University, a Fellow of the African Scientific Institute, and a member of the American Geophysical Union (AGU). In 1995 Washington received the Le Verrier Medal of the Societé Météorologique de France. In February 1997, he was inducted into the National Academy of Sciences Portrait Collection of African Americans in Science, Engineering, and Medicine. In May 1997, he was awarded the Department of Energy Biological and Environmental Research Program Exceptional Service Award for Atmospheric Sciences in the development and application of advanced coupled atmospheric-ocean general circulation models to study the impacts of anthropogenic activities on future climate. He was selected to be a Sigma Xi Distinguished Lecturer for 1998-1999. In 1998 he delivered the UCAR Walter Orr Roberts Distinguished Lecture, and a Rice University Computer and Information Technology Institute Distinguished Lecture. In 1999, Washington received the National Weather Service Modernization Award. In 1999, Washington was awarded the Dr. Charles Anderson Award from the AMS "for pioneering efforts as a mentor and passionate support of individuals, educational programs, and outreach initiatives designed to foster a diverse population of atmospheric scientists." In March 2000, Washington received the Celebrating 20th Century Pioneers in Atmospheric Sciences Award at Howard University, and in April 2000, the Colorado Bonfils-Stanton Foundation Award. In 2001, he gave the first Ralph W. Bromery lecture at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst. (Bromery was a Tuskegee Airman and later became the chancellor of the University of Massachusetts.) In February 2002, Washington was an invited lecturer at the Cleveland Museum of Natural History's Explorer Series. Also, in February 2002, the National Academy of Engineering (NAE) announced that it had elected Washington to its membership for “pioneering the development of coupled climate models, their use on parallel supercomputing architectures, and their interpretation." Washington was inducted into the NAE in October 2002. In 2002, he was appointed to the Science Advisory Panel of the U.S. Commission on Ocean Policy and the National Academies of Science Coordinating Committee on Global Change. In 2003 he was elected to the American Philosophical Society. In 2004 Washington received the Vollum Award for Distinguished Accomplishment in Science and Technology from Reed College in Portland, Oregon. In June 2006, he served as commencement speaker and was the recipient of an Honorary Doctorate of Science at Oregon State University. In October 2006 Washington was the Robert D. Cess “Distinguished Topics in Atmospheric and Oceanic Sciences” Seminar speaker at the State University of New York at Stonybrook. Washington was elected honorary member of the AMS in 2006, and received the Charles Franklin Brooks Award from the AMS for outstanding services to the Society in January 2007. Washington received a Lifetime Achievement Award from Raymond L. Orbach of the U.S. Department of Energy in August 2007. In December 2007, he was appointed to the Board of Trustees of the H. John Heinz III Center for Science, Economics and Environment. Warren's current research involves use of the Parallel Climate Model (PCM) and the Community Climate System Model (CCSM) to study the impacts of climate change in the 21st century. He currently serves as a co-chair of the Climate Change Working Group within CCSM. The Parallel Climate Model is a DOE-supported effort, and the Community Climate System Model is supported by both the NSF and the DOE.
Warren M. Washington, Ph.D., Senior Scientist -- Archives; Streep, Meryl; Black Environmental Science Trust (BEST); National Science Foundation; Gates, W. Lawrence; Bierly, Eugene W.; Simpson, Michele D.; Baker, D. James; Piton Foundation; Environmental Science; Wirth, Wren W.; Rockefeller Foundation; Malcom, Shirley; Roberts, Walter Orr; African Americans - Science; Energy Foundation; Williamson, Samuel P.; National Center for Atmospheric Research; Williams, Madeline; Cole, Johnetta B.
- Diversity Activites, 1963 - Present; 4.0 linear ft. (1 box) Box 4, Black Environmental Science Trustr (BEST) - 9 folders Box 16, Amercian Academy for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) - 12 folders Box 35 UCAR/NCAR Correnspondence - 8 folders, 1 blue binder; Warren M. Washington, Ph.D., Senior Scientist (Box 4)
  Restrictions on use and access
  Access to this collection is open, although there are some materials that are restricted. Researchers must request permission from the UCAR archivist to use those materials.
  Copywright Status
  The status of copyright in the unpublished writings of Warren M. Washington is governed by the Copyright Law of the United States (Title 17, U.S.C.).
  Scope and Contents Note
  The papers of Warren M. Washington, covering the period 1963-2007, document his scientific, professional, and advisory activities, as well as his significant contributions to diversity issues, particularly the enhancement of opportunities for people of color in science. The collection includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, speeches and lectures, articles and manuscript drafts, teaching materials, notes and calculations, clippings, awards, publications, motion picture film, photographs, oral histories, and other materials.
  Appraisal Note
  The papers of Warren M. Washington were given to the UCAR Archives by Warren M. Washington over the period 1987-2007.
  National Center for Atmospheric Research; Piton Foundation; Black Environmental Science Trust (BEST); National Science Foundation; Rockefeller Foundation; African Americans - Science
  - Black Environmental Science Trust (BEST), 1986 - 1999; BEST; Folder 1 - Proposal from UCAR to NSF Folder 2 - Proposal from UCAR to NSF, cont'd Folder 3 - Correspondence (1) Folder 4 - Correspondence (2) Folder 5 - Correspondence (3) Folder 6 - Organization Folder 7 - Plan of Action Folder 8 - Plan of Action cont'd Folder 9 - Best - Press Clippings (Box 4, Folder 1 - 9)
    Warren M. Washington, Ph.D., Senior Scientist -- Archives; National Science Foundation; Black Environmental Science Trust (BEST); National Center for Atmospheric Research; African Americans - Science
    - Correspondence Bierly, Eugene; American Geophysical Union - AGU; 1/04/1994, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Bierly, Eugene W.
    - Correspondence Bonner, William D.; Revised proposal to NSF for Recruitment and Retention of Black Scientists; 12/06/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Cover Sheet for Proposal to the NSF; Pilot Program: Increasing the numbers of Black students in the Atmospheric, Oceanic, Environmental and Related Sciences, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
      National Science Foundation
    - Certification Page for Principal Investigators and Co-Principal Investigators, 12/06/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Summary Proposal Budget, Year One Budget; 3/01/1994 - 2/28/1995, 1.0 Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Summary Proposal Budget, Five-Year Budget, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Information re: Principal Investigators/Project Directors, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - List of Suggested Reviewers, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Proposal Application; Austin, Meg; Simpson, Michele, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Table of Contents, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Appendix A; "Minorities in science' 93:Trying to change the Face of Science" Science article; vol. 262, 11/12/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF; Can be retrieved by paid subscription through AAAS (Box 4, Folder 1)
      African Americans - Science; National Science Foundation; Black Environmental Science Trust (BEST); National Center for Atmospheric Research
    - Appendix B; Black Environmental Science Trust description (BEST), WW001; Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
      National Center for Atmospheric Research; Black Environmental Science Trust (BEST); African Americans - Science; National Science Foundation
    - Appendix C; "As Black PhD's Taper Off, Aid for Foreigners Is Assailed" New York Times; 4/21/1992, WW002; Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Appendix D; Letters of Support; Baker, D. James, 10/26/1992; Einaudi, Franco, 3/29/1993; Gordon, Arnold, 12/03/1993; Hallgren, Richard E., 10/26/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
      African Americans - Science; National Science Foundation
    - Appendix E; Biographical sketches of Simpson, Michele and Washington, Warren, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Appendix F; Budget estimates; 3/01/1994 - 2/28/1999, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - UCAR's revised proposal to NSF: "Increasing the number of Black students in the Atmospheric, Oceanic, environmental and Related Sciences; Bonner, William D.; 12/06/1993, Proposal From UCAR to NSF; 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      National Science Foundation; National Center for Atmospheric Research
    - Correspondence Bonner, William D.; UCAR's proposal to NSF "Increasing the numbers of Black students in the Atmospheric, Oceanic, environmental and Related Sciences; 1/15/1993, Proposal From UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence Bonner, William D.; Williamson, Samuel P. "Pilot Program: Increasing the Number of Black Students in the Atmospheric, Oceanic, Environmental and Related Sciences"; 2/15/1994, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence re: resubmission of proposal; Simpson, Michele; Tesi, Giorgi; Williams, Luther; 6/18/1993 - 9/23/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence Williamson, Samuel P. 7/28/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence Stephens, Pam 8/18/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Proposal Application; 1/15/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Cole, Thomas; draft copy attached with handwritten notes and specifics for travel itinerary by Modahl, Ann; 2/26/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Cole, Thomas; Fulker, David (Unidata Program Center); 2/26/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Baker, D. James; Farrington, John W.; 1/25/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Dorman, Craig; Gagosian, Bob; Farrington, John W.; 11/17/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Modahl, Ann; 1/15/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Simpson, Michele; 2/25/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Draft "Increasing the Numbers of Black Students…"; 12/11/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Williams, Eddie N. (Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies); 2/03/1992, 3/16/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF; Handwritten Notes (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Appendix II; checklist for Proposal Submission, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Draft cover letter for proposal; 1/13/1993, Proposal from UCAR to NSF; Handwritten Notes (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence Williamson, Samuel P; comments regarding proposal, "Increasing the Number of Black Students…"; 11/06/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence Washington, Warren; 12/18/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF; Handwritten and typed notes (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence Bonner, Bill; 11/16/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence Baker, James D.; Joint Oceanographic Institutions (JOI); 10/26/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence Austin, Meg; Oceanography Society's mission; 11/19/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Draft Budgets; 11/01/1992-10/31/1993; 11/01/1993-10/31/1994;11/01/1992-10/31/1994, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Article Washington Post; 09/07/1992 "Black Colleges and their Communities"; Jordon, Joan, WW003; Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Article New York Times; 4/21/1992; "As Black PhD's Taper Off, Aid for Foreigners Is Assailed" New York Times, WW004; Proposal from UCAR to NSF; Original copy of article (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Article New York Times; 4/21/1992; "Black Scientists Study the "pose" of the Inner City", WW005; Proposal from UCAR to NSF; Original copy of article (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence "Ideas” for BEST; Simpson, Michele, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Annual Report from Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies;; Williams, Eddie N.; 1991, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Washington, Warren; list, Proposal from UCAR to NSF; Handwritten Notes (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Article Daily Camera, "Points of View" on Washington Post, “On the shortage of Black doctoral students”; 5/02/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
      African Americans - Science; Black Environmental Science Trust (BEST)
    - Article Time; Letters re: “Obstacles to Black Achievement”; 4/06/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence Williams, Eddie N.; 3/20/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - UCAR president’s message (n.d.), Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence; initial proposal involving UCAR and BEST; 8/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Black Environmental Science Trust (BEST); African Americans - Science
    - Correspondence NSF proposal; Simpson, Michele; 8/02/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
      National Center for Atmospheric Research; African Americans - Science; National Science Foundation; Black Environmental Science Trust (BEST)
    - NASULGU, “HEA Support for Black Graduate Programs”; 9/1992, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Article Audubon Activist, April 1992, “The Activist Forum; A Healthy World Is foremost A Just One”, Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Conversation Series:; Published by Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies; 1991; Luney, Percy R., Proposal from UCAR to NSF (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Notepad; Washington, Warren; handwritten notes (n. d.), Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Dartmouth College; 4/27/1995, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Laboratory Experience in Atmospheric Research at NCAR (Project LEARN); 8/09/1993, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Simpson, Michele; 8/02/1993, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Einaudi, Franco; 6/19/1993, Correspoondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Notes re: meeting with Wilson, George; 4/23/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Press Kit for the Congressional Black Caucuses Legislative Weekend "Environment Braintrust"; Mr. Munir; 5/06/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Clemmitt, Marcia; article in The Scientist; "Minority Scientists Broaden Efforts to Fight Environmental Woes of Poor"; 4/03/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - UN Conference on Environment and Development, June, 1992; Krenz, Maria, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Van Kehrberg, Christie IRS tax exempt; 5/09/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - National Minority Environmental Leadership Summit, National Advisory Committee; Chavis, Benjamin F. 4/15/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Simpson, Michele; Background Information and Program Ideas; 1/08/199, Correspondence (1); Handwritten Notes (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Simpson, Michele; Background Information and Program Ideas; 1/08/1991, Correspondence(1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Notes and action items; BEST (n.d.), Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - VITA of Washington, Warren M.; 2/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Golden Family Foundation; Van Kehrberg, Christie; 4/02/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Internal Revenue Service; Application for Recognition of Exemption from Federal Income Tax; 3/29/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Golden Family Foundation; Simpson, Michele; 3/22/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Itinerary for week of 2/11/1991; New York and Washington, D.C., Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Phone messages; Arterbery, Gus; Osborn, Michael, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Itinerary for Washington, Warren; 2/10-16/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Receipt from Sheraton Washington Hotel; 2/16/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Surdna Foundation/Rockefeller Foundation (n.d.), Correspondence (1); Handwritten Note (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Phone Message regarding scheduling; Allen, Barbara; Boyd, Michelle, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Biographical Sketch Warren M. Washington; (n. d.), Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Golden Family Foundation; Van Kehrberg, Christie; 4/02/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Baugh, Richelle L.; Hampton, Henry; 3/20/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: Brooks, Hooper, L., Everett, Ralph, Karel, Frank, McHenry, William E ( NSF); Spense, Talbert B.; 2/19/1991, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Schmidt, Cynthia E.; "Alliances For Minority Participation: Program Solicitation and Guidelines", Correspondence (1); Handwritten notes (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Wirth, Wren W.; Window Foundation; 12/13/1990, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Invitation to the Congressional Black Caucus Braintrust on Science and Technology; Dymally, Mervyn M.; 9/28/1990, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Article Daily Camera re: BEST; Anthes R. A; Curtis, G. W.; 8/30/1990, Correspondence (1)
    - Environmental Grantmakers Association Conference; 10/3-7/1990; Barrett, Robert C.; 7/25/1990, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence; Golden, William T.; 8/02/1990, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and Contact Names; Cole, Johnnetta B.; Little, Deidra; Paulson, Glenn; 7/26/1990, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Tentative Agenda for Ad Hoc Global Climate Group; Chemical Manufacturers Association; Cox, Geraldine V.; 1990, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Green, Frances M.; Land and Water Fund: Legal Aid for the Environment; 4/24/1990, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Young, Edward H.; NOAA; 2/27/1990, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Bierly, Eugene; Jordan, Joan; Foundation for Black Participation in Environmental Science (FBPES); 6/26/1989, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Anthes, Richard; Foundation for Black Participation in Environmental Science (FBPES); 6/14/1989, Correspondence (1); 2 Copies (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence; Roberts, Walter Orr; UCAR; 1/08/1990, Correspondence (1) (Box 4, Folder 3)